Subtitle Provide by dramacool.asia Translator [Admin.@YNG]
Subtítulos proporcionados por el traductor de dramacool.asia [Admin.@YNG]
=The Maid=
=La criada=
=Episode 18=
=Episodio 18=
Shen Yuqing.
Shen Yuqing.
The one who wants you dead
El que te quiere muerto
is your biological father.
es tu padre biológico.
I don't have a father.
No tengo padre.
His Highness favors you more than me.
Su Alteza te favorece más que a mí.
If you'd just admitted being Shen Yuqing earlier,
Si hubieras admitido ser Shen Yuqing antes,
with Father's opportunistic nature,
con la naturaleza oportunista del Padre,
he might have wavered between us.
Podría haber vacilado entre nosotros.
But you stubbornly refused to reclaim your identity.
Pero usted se negó obstinadamente a recuperar su identidad.
You dug your own grave.
Cavaste tu propia tumba.
Shen Yuanjin.
Shen Yuan Jin.
How does it feel to lose your mother?
¿Cómo se siente perder a tu madre?
For the rest of your life,
Por el resto de tu vida,
you'll never sleep peacefully again.
Nunca volverás a dormir en paz.
Lin Jifu and Madam Su
Lin Jifu y Señora Su
will haunt you forever.
te perseguirá por siempre
The Duke has arrived.
El duque ha llegado.
The Ministers of War, Revenue, and Justice have arrived!
¡Han llegado los Ministros de Guerra, de Hacienda y de Justicia!
- Xiao.
-Xiao.
Xiao.
Xiao.
Outrageous!
¡Indignante!
Who gave you the audacity
¿Quién te dio la audacia?
to threaten the Prince Regent with troops?
¿Amenazar al Príncipe Regente con tropas?
Xiao,
Xiao,
are you alright?
¿estas bien?
we didn't mean to offend His Highness.
No quisimos ofender a Su Alteza.
The troops
Las tropas
are absolutely furious.
están absolutamente furiosos.
Indeed.
En efecto.
Your Highness, please calm down.
Su Alteza, por favor calmese.
The Western Army's Six Loyalists
Los seis leales del ejército occidental
have always cherished soldiers.
Siempre he apreciado a los soldados.
When they learned
Cuando aprendieron
I was in danger,
Estaba en peligro,
in their urgency,
en su urgencia,
they inevitably overstepped boundaries.
Inevitablemente sobrepasaron los límites.
Xiao.
Xiao.
The demoness attempted to assassinate the Duke.
La demonio intentó asesinar al duque.
By law, she should be executed.
Por ley, debería ser ejecutada.
The demoness caused a mutiny,
La demonio provocó un motín,
threatening the nation's foundation.
amenazando los cimientos de la nación.
She deserves death.
Ella merece la muerte.
Your Highness,
Su Alteza,
be the Empress Dowager's order,
sea ​​orden de la Emperatriz Viuda,
we came to oversee.
Vinimos a supervisar.
Once it's time,
Una vez que llegue el momento,
the fire must be lit.
El fuego debe ser encendido.
Fifth Sworn Brother guards the border.
El quinto hermano jurado custodia la frontera.
He's always hated evil.
Él siempre ha odiado el mal.
If he hears of this,
Si se entera de esto,
he'll surely bring the Western Army
Seguramente traerá al Ejército Occidental.
straight to the capital.
Directamente a la capital.
By then,
Para entonces,
no one could stop him.
Nadie pudo detenerlo.
With all of you present today,
Con todos ustedes presentes hoy,
I'd like to see for myself
Me gustaría verlo por mí mismo.
who among you dares to rebel.
¿Quién de vosotros se atreve a rebelarse?
My lady,
Mi señora,
the Duke and senior officials have all arrived.
El duque y todos los altos funcionarios han llegado.
Don't waste this opportunity.
No desperdicies esta oportunidad
Don't worry.
No te preocupes.
I've been waiting
He estado esperando
for this moment for three years.
por este momento durante tres años.
You're not watching the secondary consort.
No estás viendo al consorte secundario.
Where are you going?
¿Adónde vas?
How does the discussion proceed in the main hall?
¿Cómo se desarrolla el debate en la sala principal?
No matter what happens,
Pase lo que pase,
when the time comes,
Cuando llegue el momento,
the fire must be lit.
El fuego debe ser encendido.
I fear the Prince Regent's retaliation.
Temo las represalias del Príncipe Regente.
Better confirm first.
Será mejor confirmarlo primero.
Lady Zheng,
Señora Zheng,
you're indeed the traitor.
Tú realmente eres el traidor.
Fortunately, my father anticipated this.
Afortunadamente, mi padre anticipó esto.
You shameless fool.
Eres un tonto sinvergüenza.
Let me go!
¡Déjame ir!
(No! Can't let Shen Yuanjin take Lady Zheng.)
(¡No! No puedo permitir que Shen Yuanjin se lleve a Lady Zheng).
Move!
¡Mover!
My lord,
Mi señor,
the rope's chafing my shoulders.
La cuerda me roza los hombros.
Could you adjust it slightly?
¿Podrías ajustarlo un poco?
I'm the Prince Regent's secondary consort.
Soy el consorte secundario del Príncipe Regente.
His Highness still favors me.
Su Alteza todavía me favorece.
When he emerges,
Cuando emerge,
I'll have him kill you
Haré que te mate
to join me in death!
¡Para unirte a mí en la muerte!
You won't escape anyway.
De todos modos no podrás escapar.
Fire!
¡Fuego!
She dares take such a risk?
¿Se atreve a correr tal riesgo?
Hurry! Drag them away!
¡Date prisa! ¡Arrástralos!
Xiyan!
¡Hola!
Save Lady Zheng!
¡Salven a la Señora Zheng!
Go save her.
Ve a salvarla.
Understood.
Comprendido.
Ye Xiyan,
Ye Xiyan,
you got a death wish?
¿Tienes deseos de morir?
You're anxious?
¿Estás ansioso?
Zip it.
Ciérralo.
Among those you must protect,
Entre aquellos a quienes debes proteger,
have I now joined their number?
¿Me he unido ahora a su número?
The demoness prophecy
La profecía de la demonio
and the assassination attempt
y el intento de asesinato
were all schemes devised by the Duke
eran todos planes ideados por el duque
to frame Consort Ye.
para incriminar a Consort Ye.
Preposterous!
¡Absurdo!
Guards!
¡Guardias!
Drag her out and beat her to death.
Arrástrala y golpéala hasta matarla.
My lord,
Mi señor,
the Minister of Justice hasn't spoken.
El Ministro de Justicia no ha hablado.
Must your reach extend
¿Debe extenderse su alcance?
beyond your jurisdiction?
¿fuera de su jurisdicción?
The assassins were the Duke's men.
Los asesinos eran los hombres del duque.
To survive, Nanxing and I
Para sobrevivir, Nanxing y yo
had no choice but serve him.
No tuve más remedio que servirle.
I've been wronged, yet I can't get justice.
Me han hecho daño y aún así no puedo obtener justicia.
Your Highness,
Su Alteza,
honorable generals and lords, please see through the truth.
Honorables generales y señores, por favor vean la verdad.
Gentlemen,
Caballeros,
you shared life-and-death bonds
Compartían vínculos de vida o muerte
with my husband.
con mi marido.
Does his death
¿Su muerte?
not strike you as suspicious?
¿No te parece sospechoso?
The Duke's lust
La lujuria del duque
drove him to assault me.
lo llevó a agredirme.
When my husband discovered this,
Cuando mi marido descubrió esto,
the Duke murdered him with his own hands.
El duque lo asesinó con sus propias manos.
Afterward,
Después,
he blamed enemy spies,
Culpó a los espías enemigos,
and then used mourning rites as pretext
y luego utilizaron ritos de duelo como pretexto
to defile me
para contaminarme
before my husband's coffin.
ante el ataúd de mi marido.
Lady Zheng!
¡Señora Zheng!
You're the wanton one
Tú eres la libertina
who seduced me.
quien me sedujo.
You schemed to enter
Tú planeaste entrar
the Duke's Mansion.
La mansión del duque.
You're lying!
¡Estás mintiendo!
Would I abandon being a general's wife
¿Dejaría de ser la esposa de un general?
to become a wronged ghost
convertirse en un fantasma agraviado
in your household?
¿en tu hogar?
Xiao.
Xiao.
My lord,
Mi señor,
do you recall this dagger?
¿Recuerdas esta daga?
Back then,
En aquel entonces,
you used it
lo usaste
to kill my husband.
matar a mi marido.
To this day,
Hasta el día de hoy,
his blood stains remain.
Sus manchas de sangre permanecen.
This Fishgut Sword
Esta espada de tripa de pescado
was bestowed upon you by my father.
te lo otorgó mi padre.
Yet you defile it with vile deeds.
Y sin embargo lo contaminais con acciones viles.
All these years,
Todos estos años,
I'm not the only one who have suffered
No soy el único que ha sufrido
under the Duke's tyranny.
bajo la tiranía del duque.
Gentlemen,
Caballeros,
you've been fighting abroad.
Has estado luchando en el extranjero.
How could you know the torment your households endured?
¿Cómo podríais conocer el tormento que padecieron vuestras familias?
Your concubine Wu,
Tu concubina Wu,
your daughter Baozhen,
tu hija Baozhen,
and your cousin...
y tu primo...
They all fell victim
Todos fueron víctimas
to this wolf in noble's clothing!
¡A este lobo con piel de noble!
Xiao!
¡Xiao!
Very well, Xiao!
¡Muy bien, Xiao!
Madwoman.
Loca.
I should've silenced you sooner.
Debería haberte silenciado antes.
Do you think
¿Crees?
I don't want to die?
¿No quiero morir?
Long have I yearned for death.
Hace mucho tiempo que anhelo la muerte.
But I don't dare,
Pero no me atrevo,
and I can't.
y no puedo.
If I die,
Si muero,
none would clear
Ninguno lo aclararía
my husband's name.
El nombre de mi marido.
My death
Mi muerte
would free you
te liberaría
to greater villainy.
a mayor villanía.
Your Highness,
Su Alteza,
these records contain
Estos registros contienen
years of evidence
años de evidencia
against the Duke.
contra el duque.
Payroll fraud,
Fraude en nóminas,
false military claims,
afirmaciones militares falsas,
and embezzle funds.
y malversar fondos.
Examine the Western Army's ledgers
Examinar los libros de contabilidad del Ejército Occidental
for full proof.
para prueba completa.
(Evidence of the Duke's crime)
(Evidencia del crimen del Duque)
Gentlemen,
Caballeros,
you've been deceived all these years.
Te han engañado todos estos años.
I beg Your Highness
Se lo ruego a Su Alteza
and everyone here
y todos aquí
to deliver justice
impartir justicia
for those women,
Para esas mujeres,
my husband,
mi marido,
and the Western Army.
y el Ejército Occidental.
Hong!
¡Hong!
Don't heed her ravings.
No hagas caso de sus delirios.
Help me silence her.
Ayúdame a silenciarla.
The Western Army's Six Loyalists
Los seis leales del ejército occidental
were sworn to live and die together.
juraron vivir y morir juntos.
Yet for your own selfish desires,
Sin embargo, por vuestros propios deseos egoístas,
you murdered Sixth Sworn Brother,
Tú asesinaste al Sexto Hermano Jurado,
raped his wife,
violó a su esposa,
and violated our families.
y violaron a nuestras familias.
How dare you
¿Cómo te atreves?
claim to be our sworn brother?
¿Afirmar ser nuestro hermano jurado?
You beast!
¡Eres una bestia!
The Duke conspired against an imperial general.
El duque conspiró contra un general imperial.
Send him to the death cell.
Enviarlo a la celda de la muerte.
The chaste widow Lady Zheng
La casta viuda Lady Zheng
bore disgrace to seek justice.
soportó la desgracia de buscar justicia.
She is innocent.
Ella es inocente.
Dear Ministers, any objections?
Estimados Ministros, ¿alguna objeción?
- You administer justice impartially.
- Administras justicia imparcialmente.
- We accept the verdict wholeheartedly.
- Aceptamos el veredicto de todo corazón.
General of the West,
General de Occidente,
Mi Hong, heed your orders!
Mi Hong, ¡atiende tus órdenes!
Yes!
¡Sí!
The Western Army needs immediate leadership.
The Western Army needs immediate leadership.
You shall temporarily
You shall temporarily
assume full command
assume full command
of the Western Army.
of the Western Army.
As your command!
As your command!
Thanks for your fair judgment.
Thanks for your fair judgment.
Send the Duke
Send the Duke
to the imperial prison.
to the imperial prison.
- Understood!
- Understood!
Hong!
Hong!
You can't do this!
You can't do this!
Hong, please!
Hong, please!
He seeks to weaken the Western Army!
He seeks to weaken the Western Army!
Hong!
Hong!
Don't fall for his schemes!
Don't fall for his schemes!
He deserves this.
He deserves this.
Karma has finally come.
Karma has finally come.
That monster!
That monster!
Finally apprehended!
Finally apprehended!
Worse than swine!
Worse than swine!
Beat him to death!
Beat him to death!
Kill him!
Kill him!
I am the Duke!
I am the Duke!
Dare any of you strike me?
Dare any of you strike me?
Who dares?
Who dares?
Monster!
Monster!
Hit him!
Hit him!
You brat!
You brat!
Hong.
Hong.
Sixth Sworn Brother can't rest in peace.
Sixth Sworn Brother can't rest in peace.
This verdict
This verdict
shall bring peace to him,
shall bring peace to him,
his wife,
his wife,
and our families
and our families
who have suffered.
who have suffered.
Save me.
Save me.
Father,
Padre,
don't you recognize me now?
don't you recognize me now?
You...
Tú...
You're...
You're...
♪I once fell into deep love♪
???I once fell into deep love???
♪Caught in a drama of love and hate♪
???Caught in a drama of love and hate???
♪Trapped in self-made cages♪
???Trapped in self-made cages???
♪To whom should I direct my questions♪
???To whom should I direct my questions???
♪Heal my wounds from past dreams♪
???Heal my wounds from past dreams???
♪Fate bestowed me both joy and pain♪
???Fate bestowed me both joy and pain???
♪Left me a kiss of love and hate♪
???Left me a kiss of love and hate???
♪Who will unravel my dreams so deep♪
???Who will unravel my dreams so deep???
♪Who will save me from this lonely place♪
???Who will save me from this lonely place???
♪Who will give me back my lonely grace♪
???Who will give me back my lonely grace???
♪I dare not ask the infatuated ones♪
???I dare not ask the infatuated ones???
♪As the moonlight thickens♪
???As the moonlight thickens???
♪What I await♪
???What I await???
♪Which heartless soul♪
???Which heartless soul???
♪Love departs, hatred persists♪
???Love departs, hatred persists???
♪I woke too soon to bygone bonds♪
???I woke too soon to bygone bonds???
♪Forgetting the lost one in old dreams♪
???Forgetting the lost one in old dreams???
♪No longer waiting for estranged souls♪
???No longer waiting for estranged souls???
♪Memories flow in the deep night♪
???Memories flow in the deep night???
♪Illuminating lonely spirits♪
???Illuminating lonely spirits???
♪Become an ordinary mortal♪
???Become an ordinary mortal???
♪Next spring will open heart's doors♪
???Next spring will open heart's doors???
♪Not seeking a specific beloved♪
???Not seeking a specific beloved???
♪Gracefully embracing affections♪
???Gracefully embracing affections???